Finding Aid for Yvonne Duffy Papers 1952-2000
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Yvonne Duffy papers 1952-2000, 1966-1999
Duffy, Yvonne.
2 linear feet
Michigan freelance writer and disability rights advocate. Biographical information, research files, published articles, unpublished writings, and audiocassettes of interviews conducted by Duffy in her research.
018 Aa 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection was accessioned in June of 2000. Donor no. 8982.
The collection is open for research.
Yvonne Duffy was born November 25, 1935 in Toronto, Ontario. Following the death of her mother in 1954, Duffy moved to Michigan, where an aunt resided. She received a B.A. in English Language and Literature from the University of Michigan in 1973, and went on to pursue a career as a freelance writer and active disability rights advocate. A survivor of childhood polio, Duffy suffered paralysis of both legs and one arm, and relied on a wheelchair for mobility.
As a freelance writer and columnist, Duffy wrote for numerous newspapers and popular and trade periodicals. From 1994 forward she was regular "Disabled in America" columnist for the Detroit Free Press and "Voice of Ability" columnist for Independent Living Provider. From 1988 to 1994 she wrote "Self-Esteem Essentials" for Independent Living. Duffy also wrote on disability issues for Mainstream (for which she was Editorial Contributor 1989 to 1991), Accent on Living, Advance, American Mover, Ann Arbor Magazine, Ann Arbor News, Apothecary, Atlanta Journal-Constitution, Bottomline, Chicago Tribune, Computer Dealer, Convenience Store News, Cutters, Detroit Free Press, Festivity, Flowers and Giftware News, Home Lighting, Hospitality, Newsday, and Quick Printing. She also contributed general articles and book reviews to Animals, Ann Arbor News, Ann Arbor Observer, Akron Beacon-Journal, Belles Letters, Columbus Dispatch, Detroit Free Press, Fort Lauderdale Sun-Sentinel, Kansas City Star, Toward Freedom, Women's Household, and The World, as well as profiles and how-to articles for various periodicals.
Duffy was particularly concerned in her writing with issues of sexuality and the disabled, about which she published a pioneering book ...All Things are Possible, in 1981. In addition to her writing, Duffy was a frequent speaker on disability issues throughout Michigan and the United States. She was, further, a member of several community organizations in the Ann Arbor area, serving on the Board of Directors of the Washtenaw Association for Community Advocacy, the Board of Directors of the Ann Arbor Transportation Authority, the Board of Directors of the Washtenaw County American Civil Liberties Union, the Board of Directors of the Ann Arbor Center for Independent Living, the Advisory Committee of the University of Michigan Clinic on Sexuality and Reproductive Health for Persons with Mental Retardation, and the Local Advisory Committee of Elderly and Handicapped Services for the Ann Arbor Transportation Authority.
Duffy's honors include the James Neubacher Award for reporting that champions the rights of people with disabilities (1993), the EDI Award for promoting equality, dignity and independence of people with disabilities in print journalism (1995) and a State of Michigan Special Tribute Media Award (1999).
For additional biographical information see the Personal--Biographical folder and essay, "My story," in Writings--Unpublished or Manuscript--Short stories (folder 1 of 2), both in box 1.
The Yvonne Duffy papers span 2 linear feet and have been arranged into three series: Personal, 1952-2000; Writings, 1968-1999; and Mixed Media. The papers include biographical information, research files, published articles, unpublished writings, and audiocassettes of interviews conducted by Duffy in her research.
Subjects:
Duffy, Yvonne.; African American women air pilots.; Handicapped women--Michigan.; Physically handicapped women--Michigan.; Taylor, Earsley.
- Personal 1952-2000
  The Personal series spans .4 linear feet and includes biographical information, correspondence, Duffy's research files on issues of interest for news stories or fiction, and undergraduate coursework from the University of Michigan. Of note within the Earsley Taylor research file are original correspondence of Taylor, an African-American aviatrix, from the 1950s.
  - Biographical 1966-2000 (Box 1)
    (includes resume, obituary, and photograph)
  - Correspondence 1992-1995 (Box 1)
  - Directory of Colleges and Universities with Special Facilities 1967 (Box 1)
  - Honors and Awards 1966-1999 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous 1998-1999 (Box 1)
  - Research Files
    - Education and Encounter 1968 (Box 1)
    - Handicapped Data 1961-1966 (Box 1)
    - Handicapped Education 1970 (Box 1)
    - Handicapped Gadgets 1969 (Box 1)
    - Handicapped Housing 1970 (Box 1)
    - Illness 1968 (Box 1)
    - Mercury Poisoning (Box 1)
    - Taylor, Earsley (aviatrix) 1952-1997 (Box 1)
      (includes photographs)
    - Urban Crisis (Box 1)
    - Vision (Box 1)
    - Women Returning to College 1967-1968 (Box 1)
    - Youth Sensitivity 1970 (Box 1)
  - University of Michigan Coursework
    - James Joyce (Box 1)
    - D.H. Lawrence (Eng 465), Fall 1971 (Box 1)
    - Linguistics (Eng 307), Winter 1972 (Box 1)
    - Philosophy of American Education, Winter 1971 (Box 1)
    - Physical Geography 201, Fall 1970 (Box 1)
    - Psychology of Adjustment (Psych 281), Fall 1969 (Box 1)
    - Speech (Box 1)
    - Survey, 373/374, Fall-Winter 1970-1971 (Box 1)
  - Walker, Ethel (aunt), correspondence and memorial program 1970-1972 (Box 1)
- Writings 1968-1999
  The Writings series spans .6 linear ft. and includes clippings of Duffy's published articles, as well as unpublished essays, poetry, short stories and a journal. Included in the Published writings subseries is a copy of her 1981 book, ...All things are possible, and associated publicity materials.
  - Published
    - Accent on Living, 1969-1983, 1983 (Box 1)
    - The Atlanta Journal/Constitution, 1993-1995 (Box 1)
    - Chicago Tribune, 1992-1995 (Box 1)
    - Detroit Free Press, 1994-1999, 6 folders (Box 1)
    - Enable Magazine, 1997-January/February 1998 (Box 1)
    - Independent Living and Health Care Today/ Independent Living, 1994-1995 (Box 1)
    - Independent Living Provider, January/February 1995-September/October 1997 (Box 1)
    - Mainstream, July 1986-September 1990 (Box 1)
    - Miniatures Dealer, February 1989-August 1990 (Box 1)
    - Watch and Clock Review, October 1987-November 1988 (Box 1)
    - Book Reviews 1982-1989 (Box 1)
    - Book ...All things are possible, 1981 (Box 1)
    - Book Publication Publicity 1982 (Box 1)
      (includes photograph)
    - Miscellaneous 1968-1999, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Unpublished or Manuscript
    - Book Reviews (Box 1)
    - Enable Proposals, 1997 (Box 1)
    - Essays (Box 1)
    - Journal, "Tea With Sugar" (Box 1)
    - Poetry (Box 1)
    - Short Stories, 2 folders (Box 1)
- Mixed Media
  The Mixed Media series, spanning 1 linear ft., consists of ten 3.5" computer disks containing files from Duffy's personal computer, and over 100 audiocassettes of interviews conducted by Duffy in her research. Also included is a National Public Radio interview with Duffy regarding her book ...All things are possible.
  - Audiocassettes (Box 2)
    (including NPR interview about her book ...All things are possible)
  - Computer files of her writings, etc., 10 3.5" floppy disks (Box 2)